Ahmed Abdelkhalek Hassanien

CLOUD ENGINEER

Cairo, EG | +201140005146 | eng.ahmed7007@gmail.com

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Multi cloud computing, Linux administration, Kubernetes, OpenStack, expert with over 8+ years of experience can design, integrate, and deploy durable Cloud solutions. Through anticipating issues in large cloud-based environments and scripting ability in Python, Bash, and Ansible, and many other tools, this experience has proven improvements and ingenuities. have excellent critical thinking skills and always focus on the customer's requirements, have implemented, and supported several clouds to address various enterprise requirements in terms of performance and ability.

EXPERIENCE

Deloitte. |Senior Cloud Consultant

Sep 2024 - Current

- Developed serverless web application using App Engine and Cloud Functions, demonstrating proficiency in cloud-native development.
- Assisted in migrating departmental applications to Google Cloud, gaining practical experience in liftand-shift and re-architecting strategies.
- Contributed to cloud cost optimization efforts by utilizing Cloud Billing reports and cost management tools
- Participated in cloud security workshops and implemented basic security best practices in test environments.
- Automated infrastructure deployment using Terraform and Google Cloud Deployment Manager, reducing manual configuration time by almost 75%
- Implemented continuous integration and continuous deployment (CI/CD) pipelines using and GitHub Actions.
- Containerized legacy applications using Docker and migrated to Google Kubernetes Engine, improving scalability, and reducing infrastructure complexity.
- Developed monitoring and alerting solutions using (Cloud Monitoring), enabling proactive issue detection, and reducing mean time.
- Created serverless data processing workflows using Cloud Functions and Pub/Sub, handling over 1
 million events per day with 99.9% reliability.

Ericsson | Cloud Engineer

Mar 2020 - Sep 2024

- Conducted over 40+ technical presentations, effectively communicating complex technical concepts and solutions to both technical and non-technical customer stakeholders. resulting in a significant increase up to 50% increase in client understanding and satisfaction
- Provided detailed technical documentation, Authored 15+ comprehensive technical documents and user guides, reports, that are clear, concise, and understandable, facilitating smooth project execution and client onboarding and reducing support tickets by 25%.
- Maintained regular contact with clients to understand their requirements, provide updates on progress, and resolve issues, ensuring maximum customer satisfaction and professional relationships.

- Collaborated with cross-functional teams, including applications engineers and project managers, on 5
 major projects, achieving almost a100% on-time delivery rate that drive projects to completion and deliver
 clear and consistent communication.
- Conducted training sessions and workshops to enhance team knowledge of cloud technologies and boost technical skills.
- Experience as an OpenStack/Linux administrator, integrating OpenStack, cloud computing, virtualization, Linux system administration, and configuration management.
- Designed and deployed clouds based on OpenStack and Kubernetes for customers.
- Managed multiple clouds for enterprises on bare metal, virtual machines, and containers to address different project needs.
- Experience with OpenStack components such as Neutron, Nova, Cinder, Horizon, Ceilometer, Heat, Glance, and Swift.
- Created and managed multiple tenants in a cloud, set quotas, triggered alarms, created networks, and customized templates ... etc.
- Experience in systems automation using BASH, Python, Perl, and Expect scripting.
- Developed more that 50+ scripts and tools with Python and Bash scripting to automate tasks and improve efficiency and reducing manual tasks by 50%.
- Experience with Docker and SQL.
- Familiarity with monitoring frameworks such as, Data Dog, Grafana, Prometheus and Dynatrace.
- Advanced knowledge in Linux system administration, working across the entire Linux stack from kernel, networking, storage, to applications.
- Practical understanding of network fundamentals (DNS, DHCP, TCP/IP, routing, switching, HTTP) and good troubleshooting skills at all levels.

Projects Management and Achievements:

- Successfully implemented NFVI environments for TE and Etisalat-Misr, receiving customer appreciation for dedication and prompt support.
- Expand multiple Clusters (Kubernetes) and NFVI for customers in Egypt and the Gulf, and north Africa managing both hardware (switches, servers, cables) and software (computes, OpenStack, Kubernetes, ...etc.)
- Provisioned and managed multiple clouds environments for enterprises, utilizing OpenStack components such as Neutron, Nova, Cinder, and Swift.
- Develop and maintained scripts for automation using Python, Bash, and Expect scripting to streamline operational processes.
- Configure and deploy servers to support new cloud-based applications, resulting in improved scalability and performance.
- Managed NFVI environments for clients like TE and Etisalat-Misr and Orange and STC, receiving customer appreciation for prompt support and dedication.
- Utilized monitoring frameworks (Prometheus, Grafana) to ensure optimal performance and reliability in a 24x7 production environment.
- Created and managed multiple tenants in the cloud, establishing quotas, triggering alarms, and customizing heat templates for resource management.

Ericsson | L2 Support Engineer

Oct 2018 - Mar 2020

- making Scripts with tools like Python and bash and expect Scripting.
- Experience in Linux Systems to manage daily tasks.
- Good with SQL query.
- Customer support engineer to manage all customers tasks and needs.
- Automation Engineer to create and maintain all daily and monthly tasks.
- Handling BSS operations in Etisalat Misr Managed Service Project.
- Troubleshooting Access network problems and outages.
- Performing BSS network configurations (parameter configuration, new features trials...etc.)
- Implementing cutovers.

- Preparing scripts for expansions and performing the expansions in the low traffic time (Hardware Expansion, signaling ...etc.
- Handling BSS performance degradation issues.
- Handling network outages and emergencies with the 2nd and 3rd line support teams.
- New node hardware and functional acceptance tests with the roll-out teams.
- Collecting the traces and dumps.
- Documented customer support processes and procedures, resulting in the reduction of customer support errors.
- Support The Customer if they have any issue and oversee those issue by Opening CSRs with global support team and follow on it.
- L1 Team Leader: Managed a team of 8 members, providing daily support and guidance. Conducted knowledge enhancement sessions, addressed team queries, and coordinated with the management team to ensure smooth operations and continuous improvement. Actively contributed to the professional growth and development of team members.

Ericsson |L1 and BackOffice Engineer

Oct 2017 - Oct 2018

- Handling performance degradation issues for access network.
- Analysis and correction of configuration errors OF Ericsson BSS Nodes.
- Troubleshooting Access network problems and outages.
- Support Field Maintenance Engineers Activities in site for two vendors (ERICSSON -ZTE).
- Perform periodical network backups and health checks to determine network status.
- Analysis RAN system and KPIs.
- Troubleshooting & technical support for all BSS related nodes.
- Handling Customer requests related to BSS end escalates it to I2 if required.
- Alarm Troubleshooting, for all BSS related nodes for 2 Vendors Ericsson and ZTE.
- Handling of tickets and issues escalating from FO or PM and other stakeholders.
- Troubleshooting & resolving all incidents, service request, Problem & trouble tickets
- Using AMOS/MOSHELL, OSS Common and other E/// tools in Troubleshooting.
- Investigation and analysis of critical technical faults for the network.

Ericsson | Performance Monitoring Engineer

Mar 2017 - Oct 2017

- Monitor the network KPI's and analyze them in case of any degradation or abnormality found for Ericsson / ZTE / Huawei.
- Making basic troubleshooting to solve the problem (if it is in team scope).
- Pre-agreed process of escalation in case the detected problem is not solved. (Performance monitoring engineer shall issue and assign TT to concerned party through TTs System relevant to appeared symptoms on network element across all network domains)
- Benchmarking reports to compare network status before and after CRs implementations.
- Event's handling: Monitoring the network KPIs in event's times (e.g., Eid event, Holidays, weekends etc.)
- Performing first level troubleshooting on the Network within Etisalat Managed Service
- Responsible for daily and weekly KPI health checks

Ericsson | Front Office Engineer

Oct 2016 - Mar 2017

- Monitoring all Alarms, Operator, Air Condition, Battery, and DC alarms (ERICSSON and
- ZTE and HUAWEI) Network.
- In case the alarm is not permanent, contact the site retention team depending on the area.

- Check onsite configuration and assist FM when needed.
- Check on internal faults on the BTS using fault codes.
- Identifying Cabinet's and TRU's Type.
- fault codes and serial no.
- Alarm log for sites.
- Monitor Internal and External Alarms of all ER/// and ZTE Sites and servers.

EDUCATION

Bachelors, Electronics and Communications Engineering.

Mansoura University | Mansoura, Egypt Oct 2011 — Aug 2016

- · Bachelors, Electronics, and Communications Engineering.
- Academic Projects:
 - o smart home based on wireless and Cloud technologies. There are many disabled and aged people who always on others for their necessities. This application helps them by allowing them to access and control every single equipment in the house from their handset easily through a mobile app. The backend of the app is hosted on a cloud, ensuring reliability and scalability.
 - Project Grade: Excellent.

SKILLS

- Cloud Technologies
- Containerization | Docker | Kubernetes | OpenShift
- Virtualization | Openstack
- Automation | Bash | Python | Ansible
- System Administration | Linux | Unix | windows
- Monitoring | Grafana | Prometheus | Dynatrace | Datadog
- SQL | MySQL
- network fundamentals | (SDN, DNS, DHCP, TCP/IP, routing, switching, HTTP, VRRP)
- YAML/JSON
- IAAC | Terraform.
- AWS | GCP | Azure
- CI/CD | Git | GitHub Actions

LANGUAGES

- English fluent
- Arabic native

REFERENCES

References available upon request.